Shahidul Islam

Phone: (571) 274-8061

Work authorization: U S Citizen Shahidul.islam.se@gmail.com

Dale City, VA

EXPERIENCE SUMMARY

Software Test automation engineer/QA analyst over 10 years of proven technical and professional experience:

Requirements analysis - Efficient in analysis quantitative and qualitative for the risk, cost, Organization structure, resources, requirements and strategy to improve the performance of the overall process.

Documentation Creation and Maintenance - Experience creating and maintaining Project Test Plans, Test Scenarios, Test Cases, Requirements Documents, Design Documents, Technical Specification-Designs, Functional Requirement Specifications, Requirement Traceability Matrix (RTM), Gap analysis.

Automation Testing – Experience, Selenium WebDriver, Java, TestNG and UFT/QTP.

Have hands on experience: in implementing DevOps/CI environment using Jenkins/Maven.

Experience: in BDD/TDD framework and technology for automation testing.

Functional Testing - Experience in System Integration, Regression testing, Positive-Negative, boundary and support UAT in windows and Linux/Unix system using Linux scripting.

Database/back-end Testing – Experience writing complex SQL queries for verifying data accuracy with front-end interactions as expected and able to verify data interactions in the database as per the business scenarios and provide technical guidance accordingly.

Performance Testing – Experience in LoadRunner and JMeter to verify efficiency, scalability, Hits per second, response times of the UAT per SLA and generate and analyze the report and provide the recommendation.

Self-motivated, details-oriented dynamic detail oriented team player, Very efficient working in multiple project parallel with priority, and capable to manage the team to ensure day to day activities and delivery.

Experience in Test Estimation effort and feasibility analysis to . Serious about learning and adopt new technology up to industry brand.

Security Clearance: Public Trust and Secret (non-active)

PROFICIENCIES

QA/ Overall testing experience (9 years)
Automation Testing Selenium/QTP (5 years)
Small business Management (4 years)
Requirement Analysis (9 years)
Java programming/ build framework (4 years)

Back end database testing (4 years)

Strategic Planning and Analysis (5 years)
Works in gov., client environment (4 years)
Mentoring the team members (4 years)
Test Planning, RTM and documenting (7 years)

EDUCATION

BA (Minor in computer science) – 1994 – National University of Bangladesh

Other Courses:

Configuration, risk and incident management certification- Skill Soft-Mar 21 2018

SD Test Engineer – External/Booz Allen – Feb 16, 2018

A+ Certificate course – Insight Institute, Alexandria

DBA Certification/MCP – Microsoft Inc.

Software Test Automation (Selenium Web-driver & Cucumber) Online courses – Udemy

TestNG/Java Framework for test automation (online course) – 2017 – Udemy

Business Management & Build Relationship course – 2007- UMS, Arlington, VA

TECHNICAL SKILLS:

Applications: Microsoft Office, PowerPoint, Eclipse and MS Project

Testing Tools: ALM/Quality Center, Selenium WebDriver, UFT, Test Complete, LoadRunner, JMeter.

Reporting Tools: JIRA, Rational Clear Case, QC/ALM, RALY, Operating Systems: Windows XP, Windows 2007, UNIX/Linux. Databases: My SQL, Oracle, Microsoft Access, SQL Server.

Languages: Java Cucumber (Gherkins), JavaScript, VB Script, Visual Basic, HTML, and Ruby.

Others: IE, Firefox, Jenkins, Maven, JAWS, and SoapUI

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE:

Senior Software Test Engineer/ Software Analyst 07/2017 to Current Fannie Mae Inc./BAH Washington, D.C.

Major Responsibilities:

Analyzing requirements, strategy, Organization structure, resources to understand business processes for developed Test Strategies.

Develop test automation Framework/ test suit, test script and manage script as per strategic plan and testing needs.

Create detailed test Plan of the project, Design documents, Test scenarios, Test script and RTM for the functional and non-functional testing process.

Setup testing environment with appropriate tools and matrices upon appropriate need analysis.

Track issue in JIRA or available tools and maintain its life cycle and create bag tracking matric for GAP analysis.

Automation testing using Selenium WebDriver, TestNG, Java and Cucumber.

Perform database/ back end testing using complex SQL queries and stored procedure for verifying data accuracy with front-end interactions and acceptance criteria.

Verify data interactions in the database as per the business scenarios and provide technical guidance and troubleshoot data issues.

Analyzing and troubleshooting to find the root causes and assist the development team in debugging and reproducing reported issues.

Create and maintain RTM and quality metrics for the assigned projects and perform GAP Analysis to maintain the standard as part of exit criteria.

Performance testing using LoadRunner and JMeter to verify efficiency, scalability, Hits per second, response times of the UAT per SLA and generate and analyze the report and provide the recommendation.

Performed requirements validation and support QA process and various testing on the scoop, such system integration and functional testing, 508 Compliance, security and regression testing. Work closely with development team to identify and resolve any system-related problems; discuss solutions and make recommendations to senior leaders; implement and test these solutions and maintain professional communications and liaison with the Test Manager, Developer, Product owner and other related team members.

Software QA specialist / Tester-III March 2015 to February 2017 Bureau of Labor Statistics (BLS) Washington DC. (Tetra Tech Inc.)

Major Responsibilities:

Analyzing requirements, strategy, and Organizational structure, resources to understand business processes for developing Test Strategies, set-up test environment and manage entire testing activities with related team players to ensure developing the AUT as expected.

Create and maintain detailed test plan of the project, User Story with acceptance criteria, Design documents, Test scenarios, Test script and Create and maintain quality matrix and RTM for the assigned projects and perform GAP Analysis to maintain the standard as part of exit criteria of the for the functional and non-functional testing process.

Create automated scripts using Test Complete/QTP for Functional and Regression testing Set up an automation test environment using Selenium WebDriver, TestNG and Java.

Support QA process and various testing on the scoop, such system integration, and functional testing, 508 Compliance, regression and UAT, Database/Back End testing with SQL query using SQL server or My SQL to verify database activities in comparison with the front end interaction.

Perform automation testing and develop a framework with Java, Selenium WebDrive, TestNG, and Cucumber.

Conduct performance testing using LoadRunner, JMeter or any other available tools as per business need.

Analyzing and troubleshooting to find the root causes and assist the development team in debugging and reproducing reported issues.

Participate and contribute to the daily stand-up meeting, requirement analysis meeting and sprint planning meeting etc.,

Provide hands-on work as well as mentor the testing team within the approach and responsibilities. Work closely with development team to identify and resolve any system-related problems; discuss solutions and make recommendations to senior leaders.

Test Automation Engineer
July 2014 to Feb 2015
USPTO Alexandria, VA (Swain Tech Inc.)

Major Responsibilities:

Analyze system requirements to develop a test strategy, set-up environment in order to perform and manage testing activities.

Create test automation test plan and set up the environment using Test Complete/Selenium WD, TestNG, Cucumber and Java. Develop the test script and manage script as per strategic test plan based on the business need.

Create and maintain requirements traceability matrix RTM and defect tracking by using Quality Center / ALM.

Experience doing functional testing in Linux using Linux scripting.

Identify and resolve technical problems with systems by comparing newly designed project interface requirements with current interfaces in the mainframe-based legacy system

Work independently as well as within a group while supporting multiple projects

Collaborate with business users and customers to clarify system requirements to improve the user interface and the design and development of the system processes.

Review system specifications for design functionality and user documentation ensuring functionality coordinates with user instructions

Perform Database/Back End testing with SQL query using SQL server or My SQL to verify database activities in comparison with the front end interaction.

LoadRunner and JMeter to verify efficiency, scalability, Hits per second, response times of the UAT per SLA and generate and analyze the report and provide the recommendation.

Work closely with development team to identify and resolve any system-related problems, discuss solutions and make recommendations to senior management.

Software Test Engineer
Sep 2011 to June 2014
SAIC, Arlington, VA (Contract)

Major Responsibilities:

Analyze requirements, understand the business process to develop Test Strategy, set-up test environment and manage entire testing activities with related team players to ensure developing the AUT as expected.

Create a detailed test Plan of the project, User Story with acceptance criteria, Design documents, Test scenarios, Test scripts and documented as per business need and provide hands-on work as well as guidance for the automation team while providing architecture/design for automation related topics. Develop manual test scripts and requirement traceability matrix.

Execute test cases manually, validate test results, and report defects accordingly using PVCS Tracker.

Create automated scripts using Quick Test Professional (QTP) and Test Complete for Functional and Regression testing.

Create and maintained Test Matrix (Requirements Traceability Matrix-RTM).

Perform Back-End database testing through the SQL queries.

Developed UAT test plans/User story with the acceptance criteria as per business requirements and support doing UAT Testing.

Participate and contribute in the weekly project status /technical review meetings, and Problem Tracking Report (PTR)/GAP Analysis meeting.

Software Test Engineer
July 2008 to August 2011
KP Inc.
Silver Spring, MD

Major Responsibilities:

Analyze requirements and developed Manual test cases for functional requirements and execute them in the Mercury Quality Center.

Create Test Plan, Test Script, create scenarios and all related documents for functional Testing and performed different kinds of testing such as Integration testing, smoke testing, black box testing and regression testing in different stages of the application development.

Perform Functional testing using Quality Center.

Develop project-specific test plans, create and maintain Requirement Traceability Matrices. Identify Test Cases for Automation, develop test Scripts for automation testing using QTP. Executed automated scripts as part of regression testing & updated test scripts as needed.

Develop automated scripts using SQL queries to performed backend testing ongoing basis.

Performed Integration testing to verify the data interface between various modules.

Reported defects using the Quality Center, monitored status and close the bugs/cases as and when fixed.
Participated in status meetings to present the project status and to report issues if there any. Communicated with developers, and other team members through all phases of testing to prioritize bug resolution, GAP analysis, and related issues.